let's look at the solution to a write
update optimization quiz where we have
two cores with write update coherence
and
we consider the case of no optimization
dirty bit only optimization and both
dirty bit and shared bit optimization
and for this program how many bus uses
and memory writes do we get so let's
consider the case of no optimization
first let us first consider the no
optimization case
this right here we'll use the bus
and we'll write to memory this read here
the first one
will use the bus
but will not update the memory because
this is a read miss
from then on each write on core 0 will
use the bus to broadcast and update
memory
so we get 999 more
accesses to each because of this
whereas reads are no longer going to be
misses
and they find what they are looking for
in the cache so they are no longer going
to either bus or memory
eventually these caches replace this but
nothing happens on the replacement in
this case because everything is already
up to date so overall here we got 1001
bus use and 1000 memory writes now let
us look at the dirty bit only
optimization
in this optimization
the writes on core 0 will all be
happening to core 0's cache and the only
write to memory will be when the block
is replaced so we get only one memory
write how many bus users do we need well
the first write and every subsequent
write will be broadcast so we get 1000
bus accesses because of these rights
we still have the one access because the
first read is a miss after that that all
hits and don't go to the bus
and now we have an additional bus axis
because the replacement of a here needs
to send the data to memory for which we
need a bus axis
so overall we reduce dramatically the
number of memory writes in exchange for
one more
bus use
now let's see what happens with the
dirty and shared optimization
we're right here and at this point we
are the only one who has this block so
the shared bit
is not set
this would normally allow us to write to
it without going to the bus anymore but
because the very next axis is read of a
on core 1
the sharing starts
and that means that really
we have exactly the same number of bus
uses and memory writes
remember that the sharing optimization
only works when we are accessing
a block only on one core this block is
actually being
read on one core written on another so
all the writes on this score need to be
propagated to the bus so that this
course cache can be updated so really
here the shared bit optimization doesn't
result in any savings